Guide to the Peter P. Hill Papers, 1965-1994 MS0352.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Peter P. Hill papers
1965-1994
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Hill, Peter P.
MS0352.UA
6 Linear Feet
Peter Proal Hill (1926- ), Professor Emeritus of History and International Affairs, was University Historian at The George Washington University from 1985-2004, when he retired. Dr. Hill earned his B.A. from Tufts University in 1949, and M.A. from Boston University in 1954. He came to GW in 1957 as a teaching fellow, and earned his Ph.D. from GW in 1966. He taught American and European history, specializing in diplomatic history. From 1984-85 he served as interim dean of the School of Public and International Affairs (which became the Elliott School for International Affairs). Collection includes committee records, faculty code, by-laws of the School of Public and International Affairs, manuscripts, meeting minutes, and memos. They range in date from 1965-94.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to the University Archives by Peter P. Hill in 1995.
Historical or Biographical Note
Peter Proal Hill (1926- ), Professor Emeritus of History and International Affairs, was University Historian at The George Washington University from 1985-2004, when he retired. Dr. Hill earned his B.A. from Tufts University in 1949, and M.A. from Boston University in 1954. He came to GW in 1957 as a teaching fellow, and earned his Ph.D. from GW in 1966. He taught American and European history, specializing in diplomatic history. From 1984-85 he served as interim dean of the School of Public and International Affairs (which became the Elliott School for International Affairs).
Upon the death of Elmer Louis Kayser in 1985, Dr. Hill took up duties as University Historian. As part of his responsibilities, he traveled to London to consult about the University's coat of arms, which was presented to GW by Britain's York Herald of Arms at the 1999 commencement ceremony. He contributed to the book "From Strength to Strength: A Pictorial History of The George Washington University, 1821-1996," which commemorated the University's 175th anniversary, and researched a number of topics related to GW's history that have been memorialized in descriptive plaques around the campus.
He is author of "William Vans Murray, Federalist Diplomat; the shaping of peace with France, 1797-1801" (1971) and "French perceptions of the early American Republic, 1783-1793" (1988). Dr. Hill was made Professor Emeritus in 1996.
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Materials in this collection include committee records, faculty code, by-laws of the School of Public and International Affairs, manuscripts, meeting minutes, and memos. They range in date from 1965-94.
Committees; Washington (D.C.); George Washington University. School of Public and International Affairs; George Washington University
- Academic Orientation Committee, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- All University Assembly (AUA), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Amendment to Faculty Code: established school wide personnel committees, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Arts & Sciences Self-Study Committee: synopsis of responses about the report on the Arts & Sciences Self-Study Committee, 05/1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ASPP: salary & tenure positions, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Budget Advisory Reports, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- By-laws: for the School of Public & International Affairs (SPIA), 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Columbian College: minutes, memoranda, & by-laws, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Columbian College Committee on Admissions & Advanced Standing (CCAS), 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Conflict of Interest Committee, Commission for the year 2000, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Criteria & Procedures for Appointments, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Curriculum Review: for the School of Public & International Affairs (SPIA), 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Departmental criteria & procedures: for hiring new, full-time faculty (A thru M), 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Dissolution of Student Life Committee, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Elliott School of Public & International Affairs, Curriculum vitas, Ad Hoc Curriculum Committee, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Elliott School reconstruction project, Spring, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Elliott School reconstruction project, Spring, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Excom: post-tenure review end of year report, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Executive Committee, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Exhibits on French Revolution: news releases, correspondence, checklist, label drafts, loan agreements, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Exhibits on French Revolution: publicity, time table, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Exhibits on the French Revolution: receptions and total cost, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Faculty agendas, expenditures, payroll, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Faculty Senate minutes, SPIA minutes, amendments made to GW judicial system, report on modified semester, correspondence, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Faculties survey, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- GW planning documents, 12/1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- History department, 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Invasion of Maury Hall by students, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Joint appointments-ASPP, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Manuscript of Peter Hill's book, French Perception, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Materials relating to procedures of English Institute, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Organizational discrimination questioner, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Paperwork on possible student membership on Faculty Senate Committees (about possible student-faculty union), 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Planning document summaries (various committees such as the Committee on Coordinated Planning, correspondence, meetings, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Poor people's campaign, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Self-study program, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- SPIA (School of Public & International Affairs) curriculum proposals, correspondence, committees, 1988-1989 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Senate Executive Committee, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Senior Executive Committee, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Spring semester, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Student-Faculty Union for an Open University, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Student Life Committee (SLC): constitutional material, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Student Life Matters, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Student power, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Student Council minutes, Student Assembly minutes, 1966-1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Tenure Review file N thru P, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Tenure Review "Done" file R thru Z, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- University crisis correspondence:, 1967-1972 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- University policy on Conflict of Interest, 1990-1991 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- University Senate papers, 1968-1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Various committees, ASPP, school-wide committees, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Various committees, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 14)